welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we call hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the stoah
I am Peter Lindbergh the Stewart of the
stoah some of you may know I run a stoic
group in Toronto Canada and obviously we
can't meet in person at the moment so
I've launched the stoah I am seeing the
stoah not only as a place to talk and
practice our stoicism surely some of
that will happen but I'm viewing it as a
digital campfire for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment today my
good friend John Verve a key is going to
share his latest thoughts on the the
meaning crisis and how it relates to
this unfolding kovat 19 situation at
first I suggested to John we call this
meeting the the meaning opportunity than
the meeting Kairos mainly because I've
been hearing a lot of people in the
circles John and I run in saying that
they have a new sense of meaning in this
moment when I mentioned that to John
John crudely suggested that we should be
careful in conflating what feels
meaningful to what feels urgent hence
the reason for the question mark of
today's title so in a more mode I'll
hand it over to John and how this
session works today after he shares his
thoughts
I'll ask him some questions and we'll
open up for the group for questions if
you have a question write it in the chat
box and I will unmute you and then just
read your question to John if you prefer
I read your question then just indicate
that when you write it in the chat box
and we'll go for about 60 minutes if it
goes a little bit over maybe 75 minutes
if that's okay with everyone so that
being said I will hand it over to John
right now
let's see I might have to mute you John
hold on can you meet yourself right now
John under yourself me now yeah I can
hear you great great okay excellent
we had me both uses so thank you for
inviting me Peter and I'm very intrigued
by the question the coming up for me
right now and so I guess what I want to
do is explore what's happening right now
and how it might be intersecting with
the meeting crisis so one thing that
comes to mind is that one thing we might
expect is that people are experiencing a
lot of reciprocal narrowing their lives
are getting narrowed their agency and
their flexibility is narrowing um
they're experiencing kind of dama side
in which a lot of places that they
thought of as their home and where they
belong where they worked are getting
truncated and of course that is
happening and I'm talking to people that
are experiencing this rather intensely
we might also see people commenting to
experience this and a really challenging
manner in that they're being sort of
thrown back onto the subjectivity in a
way that could call the way that
subjectivity from Descartes on has been
so central to us that's had such
normally a normative Authority for us
and finding that the that subjectivity
does know I have that much resources to
provide them with what they need to
confront the radical changes both the
immediate ones and potentially the more
abstract long-term ones that they're
facing so we could see that happening
we could see as Peter mentioned people
all expressing a tremendous amount of
meaningfulness coming out and this could
be due to a couple of things this could
be due to just the urgency we could be
dropping down Maslow's hierarchy of
needs and we're actually really not
dealing with meaning in life issues
we're dealing with solving a lot of very
concrete problems and so our
problem-solving machinery is getting
sort of current satisfaction that could
be happening and that could be part of
what I was alluding to when I mentioned
to Peter we might be confusing urgency
with meaning it could be that as people
are being crunched downward and they're
losing a lot of the things and this is
more of a crooked Guardian point it kept
us busy and distracted and invest in
things that we thought would give us a
sense of meaning and happiness we can
we've discovered perhaps that we can
lose a lot of this and we are forced
into the interpersonal relationships
which is what we're doing right now as
being the locus where we're trying to
satisfy our need for meaning we're
finding that this is actually a better
place to try and find meaning than the
other things we were doing before so we
could be experiencing an increased of
meaning because of a recovery of the
being mode that is actually present in
dialog we could be covering recovering
meaning because we and I've seen people
doing this we fall into a kind of
nostalgia a myth or what I might call a
mythological nostalgia the virus is kind
of like you know a Greek or an Old
Testament deity it's this pervasive
ubiquitous thing out there chaotically
sort of it's like a hyper object to use
Morton's term moving through the world
and just and changing and altering
things but in an abstract way and behind
the scenes and it seems to be demanding
a purity code from us a tremendous
purity code it feels a lot like an Old
Testament deity and so that kind of
nostalgia and let's not forget that this
is
deeply woven whether or not we're
religious is deeply woven into our
cultural cognitive grammar so people
might be picking up on that and finding
the fact that they're in this kind of
mythological narrative very meaningful
to them people might be finding it
meaningful precisely because they think
this has provided the final evidence for
the need for their particular pseudo
religious ideological utopia which they
are a certain is on the horizon there
and much like the people that Frankel
talked about in in the camps who were
certain of when they were going to be
liberated and then they of course turned
out to be the people once the date had
passed they of course collapsed and
often tried other people down with them
so what I'm saying is I think it's more
plausible and this is why I like the
term Kairos that we're in a situation in
which we're having a very complex set of
reactions to what's happening right now
I think some people are finding an
exacerbation of the meeting crisis in
ways they've articulated I think people
are maybe perhaps confusing meaning and
urgency people might be recovering the
meaning of the being mode in the as
things get crunched down to
interpersonal dialogue people might be
recovering meaning in a way that I think
is dangerous because they are falling
into a well-worn and well understood
although not very explicitly in their
consciousness explicitly aware
mythological narrative of these kinds of
mythological somewhat demonic forces at
work in the world and so I think it's
one of the things we need to do very
carefully is question in a penetrative
fashion what this what the what the
various experiences of the increase or
decrease in meaningfulness are and when
we come to a better approximation of
that complexity coming to a decision
about how we can best interact with the
car Ross because I do think
there is a real potential here because
the Kairos can tempt you towards the
good or towards the evil I think there's
a there's a real opportunity here to see
our cultural cognitive grammar shifting
in a fundamental way I'm not necessarily
saying it's going to happen but I think
there is the real potential for this to
happen and I think there's a real need
for this to happen
because I think it is highly probable
that this is not our last pandemic all
of the factors that have caused this
pandemic are still in existence and
still growing this pandemic was
predicted it has been predicted multiple
times in the last decade and the factors
upon which that successful prediction
were made are still in existence and
accelerating and I think it's highly
likely that we will come into it and I
do not think it will be a merely
additive effect the second pandemic I
think it will be an exponential effect
on the way it shakes things up and
causes sort of horrific exposure to the
possibility of a fundamental training
change in our worldview so that's my
thinking right now and that's the kind
of thing I'd like to explore if he does
great so I'll warm drum up with some
questions if you have questions you
start writing in the chat box and then
I'll call you up or read it on your
behalf so my first question John so John
and I have a regular circling practice
and I only have spoke to you once and
our practice kind of is on hold at the
moment so just to get in like a really
embodied state I'm curious how since it
started dawning on the collective
unconscious that this is was going to be
this is a big deal how did it affect you
personally and in the bodied sense so
that's very good very good question
so part of the way that became very
salient to me was the extra stressor on
me so one part of it is just my own sort
of apprehension about what's going on
part of it was picking up on the stress
it was inducing in the people that I
care a lot about because they faced real
risk in important ways
and part of it was also an existential
issue because I was struggling to
understand how to be rational in the
face of so much uncertainty and so much
shifting information I was keenly aware
of the fact that you know the
representative bias and the confirmation
bias and their you know and the
availability heuristic we're kicking in
and causing me to give wildly
inappropriate judgments of the
probability of things and I was also
aware of the fact that it was difficult
for me to devote the time needed in
order to determine the plausibility of
some of the information I was given and
I was also aware of the fact that this
was not something for which I could
merely sort of wait because of the
urgency of the risk and my actions could
definitely put other people at risk so
my substantial issue will as sort of in
competition with the stressors and also
the concern I have for the people that I
care about and who are in my care and
what that has resulted personally for me
is an elevation of my Meniere's disease
in my left ear which has been very
troubling and trying for me and so I've
had to do quite a bit to moderate that
and I've also decided the way I can take
action is to take all of the reasonable
precautions that are being advised to me
from people I respect both personally
because they have the rent of the
requisite medical and health training
and from the scientific community and
then beyond that turn to what can I do
to make a difference which is one of the
reasons why I'm here right now
it's one of the reasons why I've started
teaching my meditation course online for
free I started that on Monday and it's
phenomenologically what that has meant
for me in terms of embodiment is my
ability to take action in a way that I'm
being told by others is mattering to
them and
making a difference has significantly
reduced my stress so and then I came to
a decision point this came out in a
discussion I had with Andrew Sweeney and
Christopher master Pietro that in the
end my survival might just raw better
survival they this is a I guess a
Socratic principle is not worth
sacrificing every other principle for
which I live and so if it comes to a
place where I have to expose myself to
biological risk because principles that
I very much care about are being put at
risk then I've decided that that's in
fact what I will do and you and I we've
been texting about this and I know
Jordan you've been talking about it how
this could be a moment to ride liminal
ride the wave of the liminal oh that
well so so that's again and that that's
something that that's something maybe I
should have brought it up in your
previous question but it maybe it
belongs here because this whole
discussion that I've been having with
Jordan it's sort of bridges between my
personal phenomenology and a broader
sort of theoretical interest which is
this idea that George and I have been
exploring of course in one sense it's
connected to the religion that's not a
religion that we've already been to
talking about but it's also connected
with giving people a formulation for a
kind of deeper response to what's going
on here and this is an idea of trying to
reformulate if I'm not quite happy with
the next adjective I'm going to use but
it's the best ones from right now try to
reformulate a post religious sense of
faith what I call Socratic faith and
what does that look like and it's very
much this idea of shifting faith from
some sort of closure and conviction arm
in instead onto this idea of an ongoing
um continuity of contact with an ongoing
unfolding process within reality such
that one is able to sense a Kairos when
it's able to sense the course of events
and one develops
a always emerging always evolving
finesse with how to steer one's way
through that and so we're trying to come
up with because this is of course
exemplified in the Socratic dialogues
the way Socrates is always you know a
lover of wisdom in in on the course of
wisdom but he never claims any kind of
completion or closure upon it and you
can see the way think he's willing to
follow the argument wherever it goes and
so that kind of faith I think is the
kind of faith we need right now and I
I'm exploring it precisely because of
what we talked about already earlier I'm
concerned about the kinds of faith that
might be triggered right now obviously
there's you know two kinds of nostalgic
faith one is the faith in like I say the
mythological God demonic God out there
another is a nostalgia for let's just
get back to normal as fast as we can
let's just get back to normal as fast as
we can and also the utopic faith the
person who is convinced they have
closure now because they have certainty
as to where the future is going and how
it's going to unfold and I think both of
those kinds of faiths are potentially
very maladaptive and so part of what
I've been trying to do is stitch
together my own phenomenology in the in
the distress that I've been facing with
that those theoretical concerns in the
discussions but having with Jordan yeah
that's really really good and it seems
like in his liminal space and merging
culture wars happening with those
narratives that you just mentioned yes
yes you can already see it happening one
of the things I was worried about and
Chris and I have spoken about this we've
already seen the emergence of conspiracy
theories that are starting to gain
traction as a way of of trying to
explain as I and I you know I personally
had one thrown at me I was I did a talk
with Greg on reeks we just posted it and
you know one person was basically you
know the invective was that it's the
intellectuals and the scientists and the
theorists like me that have actually
brought us into this situation right now
so oh it's like yeah that's very very
dangerous that we start getting into
this kind of conspiratorial narrative so
I'm gonna follow people to read out
their questions again we have about 60
people on this chat so we're not gonna
get to all the questions and if you
didn't indicate that you wanted me to
read it out then just unmute yourself
and then ask your question to John so
the first question is Jordan you talked
about a civil or silver lining if you
can unmute yourself and just ask your
question to John sure Hey
so I'm gonna quickly find it so my
question is basically do you think
although this is a bit of a chaotic
statement but do you think there's
somewhat of a silver lining in that the
instant immediacy of everything that's
happening relative to the ordinary sorts
of concerns that we're being told to to
be thinking about all the time for the
media and so on
maybe the silver lining is that it's
somewhat of like a relief to people's
consensus addiction or certainty
addiction which i think is one of the
things that really drives people to get
attached to these old like legacy
sense-making or like information
laundering infrastructures right right
right I think I think that's right I
think the capacity for this to challenge
the obvious nosov common sense which how
I would put what you're saying and the
way that has been often raised to an
almost sacred level in our discourse the
way that's invoked and it's often a
cover for as you said you know very well
established ways of thinking often also
cover for very bias for the operation of
bias and trying to protect it from any
critical examination that's also at work
I think the the virus has the the real I
think it is doing this so it's more than
the potential but it has an ongoing
potential that's being actualized to
challenge that that Authority in a
profound way and
that in and of itself I don't know if
that in itself is a silver lining
because it's like criticality in a
system we're destabilizing the system
and that of course is what I'm trying to
get out with this Kairos it opens up
possibilities but it opens up multiple
possibilities so when people get their
worldview challenged one of the things
they can do is double down even so you
know the you know the you know the the
evidence of cults right so you have a
cult and it will prophesy the end of the
world and that that prophecy will gain a
certain number of adherents and then the
prophecy fails and what you what you
might expect is well that would cause
the cult to bleed away but what actually
happens is the cult doubles down and it
expands in size the doubling down they
say oh no we were wrong and it's a weird
phenomenon that people you'd think that
the failure would be enough to get
people to abandon and reject but instead
they double down and that doubling down
gives them a kind of attractive
competent confidence that sucks people
in uh and so this in fact reliably
happens it usually takes a third or a
fourth failure for the for the movement
to fall apart which is why I'm saying
well I think the next pandemic could be
the really crunchy one now I I don't
have any foreknowledge of this it could
go the way you're suggesting it could be
just this wakes people up and they see
the silver lining but like I said
there's clear evidence for and I gave
you some of it that people can go the
other way and that's a concern for me
hmm so Alex s you had a question about
death and Kairos yeah can you guys hear
me yep great thanks Peter and thanks
John for uh for your talk I was
wondering if you could talk a little bit
about the meaning of Kairos and
especially in the present moment and
especially as it relates to the notion
of death so currently we're in the
situation where we're facing you know
the possibility of death is in view kind
of
collectively also individually and we
know the probabilities
you know are different for different age
groups and so on but that is kind of in
the air yeah I think that in the
existentialist tradition which are kind
of alluded to earlier that connection is
drawn between you know kind of authentic
existence and Heidegger essentially yeah
yeah how many if you could say maybe
more about that and especially as it
relates to you know trying to have a
more rational wise approach to the
situation you know rather than going to
yeah thanks that's a great question and
I want to answer to that and IIIi think
you're one of the things that's really
interesting
mr. does this in her book beyond faked
and she actually holds out stoicism in
connection with this because the we we
have this word fatal and we associate it
with death in particular but what we've
come to do is it's like the way we think
of mad as being angry we're mad of
course means losing your sanity and one
of the things that could cause you to
lose your sanity yeah is your anger a
fatality originally meant the way
reality moves of its own accord the
hands of fate in that sense no not in
some magical sense but in the sense that
the universe is unfolding for things
beyond our can and it will behave the
way it's going to behave for its own
reasons right and and so death was just
one very significant instance of the
fatality of all things that and visitor
talks about the fact that stoicism tried
to pull apart that by making a
distinction between the things that are
largely in the grip of nature and then
the meaning we give them which has to do
you know with our cognitive processing
and our framing and pulling those apart
she said was one of the you know the
deepest ways of trying to get people to
be able to accept the fatality of all
things because the fatality actually
points to a deep confusion between the
meaning and the event now the
interesting thing about that is you see
of course this being taken up by both
Nietzsche and kirkegaard especially and
the way in which I think we can stitch
together this notion of fatality and the
and the themes you brought out around
things like authenticity is that um
there's a way in which the fatality of
all things is present - with us always
which is our mortality and our mortality
doesn't mean the event of our death it
means that like everything else we are
deep even our own bodies and you see
this in stoicism right even our own
bodies are subject to that kind of
fatality that's what the virus can show
we think we've made health into a god
and we are the masters of our health
well no we're not no or not right I mean
we can make we can move things around
and we can share probabilities but
whatever narrative we have for ourselves
in our bodies the the universe is going
to unfold in our bodies independently of
that narrative so the are the foot we
can we can deal with the one of the
first and primary ways we have to deal
with the fatality of all things is we
have to deal with it insofar as our own
bodies our own Fame our own status which
is our mortality which is different than
just the event of our death and I think
one of the things that the virus can
potentially do for us is make us step
back and become mortals again which is a
very different project than what we have
tried to be for a long time through the
way we manipulate media and the image
which is we we behave it act as if we're
immortal and then when it becomes clear
that we are in fact mortal we are we are
disenfranchised packaged away removed
from media you know etc etc and I think
instead if we could come to a place
where we can reimburse our mortality I
think that would be a good way for
extending the notion of authenticity off
of just being true to oneself which i
think is a very poor
framing of authenticity and get it
getting it back to living with the
fatality of all things in as rational a
manner as possible that's all I would
answer that question I jump in with just
a quick follow-up please please so I'm
wondering that would you would you align
the existential tradition more or less
with stoicism I don't need to say all
stoic yeah well yes and no because you
know the Mutua is deeply influenced by
stoicism and you know in crooked art
writes his PhD dissertation on Socrates
so there's obviously at least a deep
Socratic influence in crypto garden so
both of the you know the Godfather's of
existentialism I think are deeply
influenced by this current however I
would not I would not identify stoicism
with existentialism because
existentialism I think and I sorry I
mean the posts are trian sense of
existentialism not what's going on in
Heidegger because Heidegger is a
different thing
Heidi periods you know we are the beings
whose being is in question that's a
that's a different thing but the the the
the the strand that comes out later at
least one strand of existentialism that
sort of became more prominent was the
idea you know that our you know that our
existence precedes our essence because
we are the creatures who completely
decided our essence so there's a there's
a shift from Heidegger from us being the
the beings whose being is in question to
us being the self defining beings and
stoicism I think is much more careful
about that we're not completely self
defining beings there's a lot of there's
a lot of about us over which we have we
do not have control as epictetus
famously pointed out and so whereas
self-definition gets becomes quite
significant maybe even inflated in
certain searching like strands of
existentialism and you and you lose that
that you know you lose that that that
we're inherently in question I think
stoicism has much more of you know it's
not that we're completely self-defining
it's more that we can aspire to a kind
of universal logos a universal
rationality that is the proper response
for our confrontation with fatality so
that's how we pull them apart okay so
I'm gonna read this question on behalf
of isaiah's you mentioned conspiracies
but I'm wondering how we can as regular
people relate to the elites at a moment
like this it's it's becoming clear that
those more fortunate have quicker access
to testing for the virus
eg Prince Charles NBA players Hollywood
actors yep yep so this is always the the
trick of grandness sorry I didn't mean
trick in the sense of deception I'm in
it in the sense of them you know the the
the thing that requires finesse so how
do you identify how do you distinguish
identifying bonafide socio-economic
let's use that as a broad socio
political socio-economic in justices
unfairness how do you distinguish them
from conspiratorial thinking and and I
guess the idea well this is what I do I
have a heuristic is that I don't believe
in in conspiracy theories until I get
you know evidence of them that's as good
as any scientific theory or at least
moves in that direction so if you get
here you know if you get undisputed
evidence that people have this kind of
access which i think is happening no
one's calling it into question there's
no plausible alternative
explanation for the purported 'no sit
doesn't invoke any initially implausible
entities in their own right
it belongs to an already plausible
history of the wealthy and the rich
manipulating things to their own purpose
then i think that's how you sort of make
the decision so maybe i'm what in fact
proposing is we reserve the term
conspiracy theory or something that
gains its exceptions primarily just
because it proposes a conspiracy that
makes sense of what is otherwise chaotic
whereas coming to a conclusion from a
lot of evidence and argumentation that's
convergent are they plausible rationally
excess of rationally criticized and
rationally accessible that certain
groups of people are behavior being
unjustly and appropriately i don't think
we should call that a conspiracy theory
at all i think we should say no we
should say what it is we have good
evidence that people are acting unjustly
and that they should be criticized and
this is and and and then we should
criticize the structures that have made
it so easily
doable for them to engage in such
unfairness and manipulation that's what
i would say to that
so I'm going to read this on behalf of
Nikolas you talk a lot about people
maybe waking up what actions can we take
to help more people wake up propagate
good information step into dialogue
anything else well yeah I mean so not
only just I mean yeah obviously probably
get good information and that's what I
try to do with the video series and try
to do with other videos but also
propagate the skills I mean that's like
Peter and I are working so hard on
trying to come up with you know you know
a pedagogical program of putting up a
various the psycho technologies into an
optimal sequence for transitioning
people without them having to make huge
investments in a philosophical education
or into a particular ideology or
metaphysics moving them for however
nevertheless from you know oppositional
bad faith confrontational argumentation
all the way through to you know a kind
of philosophy a-- not philosophy but a
kind of Socratic dialogue in which they
feel fluent and capable of participating
that can afford them gaining access to
the power of collective intelligence and
hopefully participating in of
transforming it into collective
rationality or perhaps even collective
wisdom I think trying to
reverse-engineer the psycho technologies
the meta psycho technologies enact and
exemplify them and try to teach them to
others that's why I'm also teaching the
meditation course for free we need to
get not just the information in the
sense I mean II didn't mean just that so
forgive me around imposing on you but we
need to get more than just the ideas out
is what I'm trying to say we need to
actually teach people a broad set of
skills ecologies of practices we need to
start doing it right now and that's what
I meant is what I'm trying to do and we
need to reverse-engineer as MIT we need
to reverse engineering we need to
reverse engineer your missing psycho
technologies precisely like dialectic
hmm it seems like an interesting
opportunity now that a lot of people are
on Zoom and having these conversations
that's easy to practice
yes very much very much Samir you had a
question about the urgency effect yeah I
try to rephrase it with what has been
said to get back on them meaning this
and the Kairos I have them you know like
I don't really understand this Kairos
concept I have the impression is a kind
of Christian I did the way we are seeing
it I'm seeing like it's a kind of
Christian time of Apocalypse of the
rapture you know the moment where
everything is like changing but for me
the the Kairos is more a subjective
reality where it is in a chain of of
salience of of meaning of synchronicity
where someone have it as a changing
moment you follow me not completely I'm
not first of all a Kairos doesn't limit
you to the apocalypse the apocalypse are
just a culminating Kairos it is it is a
notion it comes out of the sort of
platonic Christian yeah it's about any
important turn right being able to sense
where that turn in and participate in it
are the turning of events yeah yeah but
I have the impression that at least I
mean for our society it is this is if
moment not by itself not because as you
said it is just abandon me we can see
it's a small one there are gonna be many
others but we are now in a synchronicity
of so many crises that we have been
kicking the can down the road that this
is like the drop that is that is you're
feeling the jar you know and also I
would say that the
the urgency thing is that it's too fast
to build to wisdom at this time for two
reason first it's because we're living
it in in life like with so many
information and it goes so quick so you
have this reciprocal narrowing were you
just going time from time and you don't
take the step back to see the big
picture of the meta-crisis and also so
so yeah I just leave it there and I let
you comment because I see it as as a
Kairos at least for for our time and my
generation so thank you for explaining
it because I have a better understanding
and yeah I don't I don't think the I
agree with you
and if I presented it as otherwise I
apologize because I might have been
misleading I agree with you that I think
there's a synchronicity to use near term
between this particular biological
crisis and the already existing
meta-crisis I think you're right and I
think it's in in that sense it's a
Kairos in the sense of also being a
tipping point and here I'm talking about
like a dynamical systems where you can
perturb a system for a very long time
and it can it can adaptively restructure
but when the perturbations get too great
a coil is critical and it starts to
break and then that criticality is a
real opportunity in a sense it because
it can go one of two ways the system can
collapse or that criticality actually
breaks the structure up enough that a
new structure can emerge out of it and
so it I agree that I think the virus is
in that sense it's it's sort of a it's
it's it's the you know the proverbial
straw that's breaking the already
overburdened camel's back the the idea
about the urgency because it's very hard
to cultivate wisdom right now I
understand yeah it's very difficult for
people to engage in the practices and
therefore
giving in to kind of urgent short-term
scarcity thinking is going to come very
naturally and so it's I think it's going
to be a very significant challenge as
you said to get people to step back and
see the bigger picture like here's where
a lot of you know a lot of practices a
lot of psycho technological practices
are really important people a way to do
this without having to argue at great
length with people and we already have
independent evidence from this control
level theory is to get them practicing
things like the stoic view from above
that transformation of perspective all
knowing really does have a huge impact
on people's propositional and
inferential thinking and it also opens
them up to a kind of reciprocal opening
it opens them up to a kind of wonder in
which they're willing to call their
worldview and their sense of identity
into question precisely because of the
way the practice alters what is normally
an unchallenged salience landscape in
which their own particular urgent
narrative is super salient and blinding
them to the bigger picture
now you understand I'm not prophesying
that this is going to spread you know
throughout the culture or anything like
that but what I'm saying is there are
things we can offer people even in their
urgency that are designed to work right
now in the urgency and can ultimately be
made conducive to and coherent with much
more long-term rational processes thank
you thank you that was an excellent
question and thank you for for
explaining it to me better youth you
clarified it very well sorry for my
confusion of so but I love your work I
love your framework I'm using it all the
time really
yep psychoactive and powerful thank you
for your work well thank you thank you
for your question I appreciate a lot
Erin Rogerson you had something about a
digital Church
[Music]
uh Aaron would you like me to read it
out oh I can hear me now yep
okay the pandemic is prompting a lot of
us to come together online and I've been
able to skip around to different
philosophy meetup groups really easily
that have been forced to move online
very suddenly and make a lot of really
interesting connections in a very short
time people seem unusually open
vulnerable you going to connect right
now and the technology like zoom is
keeping up with this pretty well and
seems like it'll only get better so I'm
wondering if the religion that is not a
religion is something that will gain
traction might it be something that is
primarily an online phenomenon like that
almost like a digital Church or it's not
30 I can't really see that now sorry I
would just was apologizing that I can do
dropped you as I apologized I'm sorry
apologize for my apology that's an
excellent question and I think that I
think that's right
you know and joy who's been talking
about that Jordan Hall and he's perhaps
the person to talk a little bit more
about he's talking about not only the
way the virtual world can afford this
he's also talking about the fact that
you know we might be able to get it to
integrate with some machine learning to
really optimize the way in which we're
connecting and the way we commit some of
the connections can be made outside of
sort of individual cognition and so I
think there's a tremendous potential for
the technology I would like I would like
to point out something it's also
connected to your question and
strengthens your point and this came up
with somebody was talking it was just
you know doing an online wisdom lecture
for web of wisdom and this came up
sort of this issue about that this
technology does something there there it
brings with it a phenomenological
difference that is actually really
important with and here's a couple of
the phenomenological features that came
up in the discussion I was having with
this person notice how close your face
is in terms of the size it fit it fills
on my visual field and yet normally if I
was that close to you and you mean you
and I just met
would be like oh but it's okay in this
medium it's part of the grammar and so
there's there's this right there's this
kind of a phenomenological intimacy
notice that also we're sort of
equidistant from each other because we
you know because we're not actually
spatially oriented we're and we're in
this digital space where everybody sort
of has equal access and that's a really
really interesting phenomena because it
also right removes a lot of the typical
ways in which people are marking
identity and status by their spatial
positioning that sort of removed and
it's put into the background in a deep
way now I was talking about either way
this really enhances the this technology
it's not only what I'm trying to say
it's not only the way the technology
furthers the communication gives us
access it's also transform it in it's
also transforming a phenomenological
experience in a profound way and I think
I suggested to her that's only a
suggestion I'm making to you but I think
it's the only thing that's analogous to
us and people are also but we're also
doing this before the crisis in our
heritage is people sitting around a
campfire because when people are
circling around the campfire they sort
of have that circular distance from each
other and because of the way campfires
their faces tend to be very well lit and
they all are oriented and Matt Rossano
actually talks about that in
Supernatural selection how that really
probably drove our cognitive evolution
in a very powerful way because we've had
fire across several species in a a drove
working memory it drove our orientation
it probably he said we said we probably
gained the ability to meditate from sort
of sharing the focus of the fire and
then looking up in this intimate fashion
to people's faces so I think we're doing
virtual camp firing or something like it
right here right now and so it's not
just sort of the the the increased power
of communication and connection
I think the medium also has the
potential if properly used artistically
and dialogic Lee to really tap in to
that phenomenological difference and
that primordial right association and
greatly empower what you're suggesting
the ability for people find something
more like a church because I think
before there were ever any churches
there was the religio around the
campfire for several species and for
hundreds of thousands of years
hmm thank you I just wanna add something
I noticed with I have a meetup group and
we meet every two weeks and going to
zoom has actually greatly improved our
ability to have a meeting in a way that
surprised me because I would have
thought you the opposite I was like
zooms not gonna work but everything
seems much easier it flows this better
way we're kind of jamming it's better
the way yes I think it's a campfire
effect yeah I think I really do I'm sort
of trying to sort of coin that the
virtual campfire effect and what's
interesting is the contrast to online
teaching where that's normally meant
like online lecturing so pretty clearly
the evidence shows that if you go to
like an online university you don't get
as good an education as if you do it in
person so I don't have anything to say
about that I just want it was a note
that because I agree with you when we're
doing this dialogic thing we seem to
find this this virtual stuff enhances
enhances the process but when we're into
sort of the dissemination the
traditional dissemination of information
in sort of you know a propositional
largely propositional format you seem to
you seem to find a significant
degradation in what people get from it
okay thank you John your hero
keep it up ho thank you for your
encouragement yeah so Dan Feldman you
had a question yes I had a question our
first first professor fare-bear by Aki
there Bakke I really enjoyed your series
and it's kind of inspired me to create
my own my own series that I'm thinking
about doing
call me done please come join you John
yes yeah yeah basically just transition
awakening from the system from systemic
inertia so my question is
what I'm an American so what can we do
and and other people in similar
situations what can we do to ensure that
the ideas and practices that are
selected in response to this Kairos move
into a wise and regenerative direction
of reciprocal opening yeah and not into
an ignorant and extractive direction a
reciprocal narrowing in light of the
fact that the techno managerial elites
and power are coming forward with a
doubling down of further privatization
austerity yeah and because there's a
there's a bailing out they're moving to
a bailing out of the corporations and
not to some kind of ubi or or to helping
out the spreading precariat and the
small businesses and such yeah sorry I
just I'm just yeah I'm just like yes
everything you're saying and I this a
similar thing came up in the rebel
wisdom thing it came up in a really
interesting way because I was posed a
question and it was an honest question
it wasn't somebody being manipulative or
anything and they basically said well
you know who's approached you have you
been approached by any of the you know
the power holders about any of it you
know
and I thought about it and I thought no
not a single one I've not been
approached by any of the people that
will power I'm not saying that the Prime
Minister should call me I mean me or the
people I'm talking with I don't know of
anybody that's been approached now are
lots of other people approached well
here we are here's your answer
like I I am busier now than I was when I
was you know going into work at the
University more and more people are
reaching out more more people like so
the bottom up is Titanic overwhelming
and the fact and this is why I'm worried
about the Kairos right and why I'm
worried about the doubling down on this
pandemic the fact that the powers that
be seem to be completely oblivious to
this whole dimension and even to the
dimension of meaning in well-being right
uh it's just
that that is something that causes me to
be that's when I think the Kairos is
gonna steer very negative in that we're
going to get a doubling down and we're
gonna get let's get everybody back let's
get everybody back to work let's get
everybody you know let's get let's get
things back to normal as fast as
possible because that's the way we're
gonna no no no no no no right that's
that's the way we're gonna do a deal
with this um and so I I share your
concern so what I'm gonna answer now is
an answer in terms it's a moral answer
which is different from a probabilistic
answer I think the moral thing for me to
do is doing what I'm doing which is
reaching out offering trying to get
skills trying to get people talking
giving people resources educating them
right getting people to seriously
challenge the obviousness of common
sense seriously challenge you know the
status quo cultural comp I think that is
the right thing to do and I think it's
the right thing to do for some of the
arguments you've already heard me give
is there an opportunity here that
heightens the chance that that will get
gained subtraction and succeed I think
there is do I predict that it's going to
succeed no I don't I suspect I hope one
way but I suspect that we are going to
get as much as we can to clamp this all
down and try and strangle it off and
[Music]
what we all have to do is keep these
camp fires burning and keep things going
because as I said this is not the last
time we're going to confront this and
the next time things
sorry I don't want to sound overly
dramatic but I think the next time
things are gonna fall apart more and so
getting people getting created more of a
bottom-up resiliency in this system I
think is going to be needed sorry that
was
pessimistic answered but I was trying to
give you as honest and realistic an
answer as I can while at the same time
trying to indicate what I think the
moral response is I appreciate that if I
could if I could just add in I'm quite
active in working together on
participatory democracy movements around
the world with extinction rebellion I
reach working with some groups with the
extinction rebellion and trying to
internationalize you know people's
assemblies citizen assemblies building
up that hollow democracy we we
essentially have representative
oligarchies yes yes we have to we have
to build that democratic movement but I
don't want to I want to take the floor
that's an important point no no first of
all keep doing that and you know and I
think that's important and there's a
there's there's a way in which my work
in your work converge because as I've
been trying to create both the the
language and the example of shifting
from adversarial processing the
winner-take-all destroy the opposition
back to a shared commitment to the
opponent processing right of the process
that above being a Republican or a
Democrat I'm committed to democracy in
the process of democracy that's where I
think my word and your word actually
converge in an important way now I agree
I agree yeah I'd love to follow up on
this in another forum if possible
sure so Joe you had a question that was
similar about game a and game B if you
still want to ask it just just go off
new sure screams I wrote in the eyes of
regular people who aren't there excuse
me in the eyes of regular people those
who are in positions of strategic
leverage the heads of industry
government education things like that it
seemed to be locked into a sort of game
fundamentalism it had been for many
decades this is the sort of blue church
idea my question to you is does the game
be crab - what you know about have any
concrete plan from going secondly from
nudging these people's decisions to
actually transforming their framework
because obviously we've heard
individually upgrading our sovereignty
being able to be more effective agents
individually but I don't know if maybe
behind the scenes there have been talks
on how to scale that up if that's at all
possible there have been and I mean I'm
gonna I mean I'm a talking with the
person who gave us the gmae gave me blue
church Jordan all and part of that is
this idea which is the religion that's
not a religion and coming and trying to
come up with a post religious faith
because here's the idea this is probably
the most radical idea I want to do what
like Augustine did as the Roman Empire's
is falling he laid the foundations not
single-handedly and I'm not saying I'm
Augustine so please I'm just using this
as an analogy okay but what they did is
they laid the fact they laid the
cultural cognitive grammar for an
entirely different culture and they
stole the culture bottom-up from the
imperial system now it didn't the
imperial system at some point then
clamped down again but nevertheless we
shifted to the middle that we shifted
out of antiquity we shifted to a
different world and so I want to try and
do that I want to try and create the
systems of meaning the the religion
that's not a religion the ecologies of
practices the communities the networks
of communities all of this is already
happening really empower it both in
terms of its grammar give it the best
scientific tools for engineering the
practices and the ecology of practices I
basically want to steal the culture from
the people who have been abusing us for
such a very long time and I usually
don't speak politically you because I
think that political framing is often a
deep misrepresentation of the issue at
least the way in which political
discourse has been as you said it sort
of been ossified and I think this also I
think Dan was pointing out that - the
way it's been ossified in ways that make
choice no longer sort of really relevant
so all right this is my most radical
thing I guess I'm gonna say I want yeah
I want to help steal the culture away
steal it away and do everything I can
and you know Christianity stoled the
culture away from the elites it's time
now if new elites form they always will
but the culture changed and it changed
in an important way and that's what I'm
trying to do right now and that's that's
what I see myself doing with a lot of
these other people that's very noble and
you certainly have a lot of people who
aren't in those positions I mean if
you're a mind you've sort of grown up in
the world sort of looks like it's
running backwards so it's hard to even
imagine that it's been that way for
decades prior but this decade certainly
feels like it's going there's going to
be some collision between the sort of
fresh traded emerging game be tights and
the sort of entrenched game a leaders
the whole point about the whole point
about the metaphor is we can't we can't
win by playing the game that's right and
so my way of trying to understand what
it is to not play their game and to
shift over to in a totally different
game to shift the culture it's to steal
the culture and the way to do that the
way we've right the only thing I can get
from history that's been able to do that
are religion but for reasons that I've
articulated I don't want not personally
I mean in terms of the functionality I
don't think the standard model the axial
age model of religion is going to do
what we need in order to steal the
culture as deeply as we need to steal it
so John do you have time for one more
question
yes I do Taylor hawk
would you like to read your question
yeah thanks I could do that yeah John I
wanted to check with you I remember you
talking about in some different contexts
about like the urgency less sort of
coming into contact with our meaning and
yep how I've seen it is like growing up
and I'm wondering like Gilead will see
you other way and yeah given the like
this situation and how quickly it sort
of seemed to come up on us obviously
lots of people were raising the flags
but it came out as quickly and given
your having valid suspicions that this
is not the last time it's gonna happen
I'm wondering how are we going to
develop or grow up even more quickly
like it seems even more urgent so that
we I don't we can mitigate this chance
of descending into chaos if you know we
have a second wave of this in a short
term I just we we need to we need to
well sort of it dovetails with the
previous question we need to accelerate
the all the bottom-up and top-down ways
in which we're trying to steal the
culture I mean and you know well - I
mean the work you're doing both the
circling work you're doing and the
attempts to innovate it in ways that you
know that I'm deeply in concert with
about trying to bring back something
like deal dialectic and via logos and
it's sorry I I don't want to look like
some sort of Marxist learn in this
poster or something but we you just need
to do more right we didn't we need we we
just we got it we got to do more we got
to speed up and we have the virtual
campfire effect and we have what's
happening here and we have that many
more people are willing to call into
question the previously unquestioned
authority of common sense and well
that's the way we've always done it kind
of thing and so I mean there is a Kairos
here I like I said I'm not that
optimistic about it turning you
now but nevertheless I do think it's
going to erode things things are going
to be reassembled but they're going to
be a much shape year round and that
shake that that's shaking up at the
foundations creates more interesting
more spaces through which we can weave
this alternative culture that we need to
do so III mean I don't want to sound
like boxer an animal farm but you know
there's a sense of which we just right
now we've got to do more of what we're
doing and make use of the best of the of
the emerging properties of of the of the
psycho technologies and the cyber
technologies to try and be force
multipliers for this I'm sorry I can't
say anything too profound to your
question it's a really good question but
that's that's that's all I can see to
say right now yeah keep on truckin more
accelerate I mean so I mean and that's
why Jordan John and I are talking about
this sense of faith that's about leaning
into the acceleration of change and you
know surfing the wave of uncertainty to
use Andy Clark stern well they used it
for slightly different purposes right
but you know I used the example from
Conrad of the captain Alliston who's the
ship is been right the ship has been
swamped and there all those sailors are
clinging to the side of the ship and
Alliston stands and he watches and he
waits and he's he's watching and he's
sensing the unfolding of the wind and
the wave and then he goes now and he
gives three orders and they do this
stuff and they write the ship that's the
kind of faith I'm talking about
I feel touched hearing that thanks John
thank you tiller also again really good
to see you missed you so I'll close in a
moment but John is journey closing
thoughts that you would like to have for
this digital campfire that we are in
right now
I hope that my pessimism is only will
only conduce realism and not any kind of
defeatism in people I hope that's clear
because that was my intent and I I I do
think that it's important that we try as
much as possible to not just talk about
this but exemplify a new way of being to
people that these are the function of
these especially because of the
virtuality of it is not just what's
happening here now but we right and we
are also exemplifying a new way of being
a new kind of as I said culture a
culture of Awakening and we have to pay
attention to and take seriously that
responsibility and rule our manner of
discourse is just as important as the
matter of our discourse that's the final
thing I would want to say about them mmm
that's beautiful so in a moment I'll
make some announcements of what's coming
up in the stoah but first John my friend
thank you so much for coming and
delivering this talking your vision
answer Thank You Graham I appreciate it
thank you so much everybody
I really enjoyed this and I really
enjoyed the discussion and just I really
I can't address you all individually
because there's been so many of you but
I just want to say so many of you gave
me so much encouragement and that really
matters to me and I don't mean just in
an equal inflationary way you know let's
put that aside this is often very
challenging for me for a lot of reasons
I'm naturally socially phobic I have
Meniere's disease there's all kinds of
things that could hold me back my
partner was sort of joking with me today
she said you know you're such an
introvert but you really act like an
extrovert there's this problem washed
out there and you do all these
connections and so what I'm saying is
you got the encouragement really helps
me it helps me overcome my introversion
my social phobia deal with my you know
the challenges of manures and so I'm
very appreciative of the encouragement
so I want to thank everybody very much
for that mm-hmm and imagine we'll have
another session at the store with you
John so we can have a round two with
this so tomorrow we have two events
noteworthy at the stoah Jordan Hall is
going to do a situational assessment at
12 p.m. Eastern Time
and I'll send you the the way to bars
repeat everything in the chat box and we
also have an existential dance party at
7 p.m.
Colin Morris from the Zion 2.0 podcast
he's a dancer so he's gonna have like a
group and body dance
there's just quite fun and - yeah and we
have about 11 events lined up just go on
the website sign up for the mailing list
get updates and to lean on the digital
Church and then the digital basket that
we pass around I'm viewing the stoah as
a gift to the world right now that
everyone could freely use and if you're
inspired to give a gift in return it
could be in any form an idea support
just go to the website and go gift
economy at the bottom and you can
provide it there thanks everyone for
coming out today really appreciate it I
think it's all together and doing this
and Wow what time is Jordan speaking
tomorrow it's at 12 p.m. Eastern time
and he'll be recorded if you can't make
it I'll post it on yeah I might be able
to make it I'll have to see things are
very much in flux for me day by today
cool
I'll text you about the link thanks
Peter thanks again for inviting me and
putting this together but yeah thanks
again everybody
take care